<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The national convenant of the Kirk of Scotland and the Solemn League and Covenant of the three kingdoms</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4231C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22584</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12061484</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12061484</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33102)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 864:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The national convenant of the Kirk of Scotland and the Solemn League and Covenant of the three kingdoms</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by a Society of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
                  <note>The confession of faith.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53240:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53240:1"/>
            <p>THE NATIONAL COVENANT of the Kirk of SCOTLAND, And the SOLEMN LEAGUE AND COVENANT of the three KINGDOMS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by a Society of Stationers, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:53240:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53240:2"/>
            <head>The Nationall Covenant, Or <hi>The Confeſſion of Faith, ſubſcribed at firſt by the Kings Majeſty and his Houſhold, in the year of God,</hi> 1580. <hi>Thereafter by all ſorts of ranks in the year</hi> 1581. <hi>By ordinance of the Lords of the Secret Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and Acts of the Generall Aſſembly, Subſcribed again by all ſorts of perſons in the year</hi> 1590. <hi>by a new Ordinance of Counſel, at the deſire of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly: with a generall Band for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the true Religion, and the Kings perſon. And ſubſcribed in the year</hi> 1638. <hi>By us, Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Barrons, Gentlemen, Burgeſſes, Miniſters, and Commons, then underſubſcribing. Together, with our reſolution and promiſes for the cauſes after ſpecified, To maintain the ſaid true Religion, and the Kings Majeſty, according to the Confeſſion foreſaid, and Acts of Parliament. And now, upon the ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Generall Aſſembly to his Majeſties high Commiſſioner, and the Lords of his Majeſties ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Privy Counſell, ſubſcribed again in the year</hi> 1639. <hi>by Ordinance of counſel, and Act of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E all, and every one of Us underwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, proteſt, that, after long and due Examination of our own Conſciences, in matters of true and falſe Religion, We are now throughly reſolved of the Truth, by the Word and Spirit of God; and therefore
<pb facs="tcp:53240:3"/>We believe with our hearts, confeſſe with our mouths, ſubſcribe with our hands, and conſtantly affirm before God, and the whole World, that this only is the true Chriſtian Faith and Religion pleaſing God, and bringing Salvation to man, which now is by the mercy of God revealed to the world, by the preaching of the bleſſed Evangell, and received, believed, and defended, by many and ſundry notable Kirks and Realms, but chiefly by the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Kings Majeſty, and the three Eſtates of this Realm, as Gods eternall Truth, and only ground of our Salvation, as more particularly is expreſſed in the Confeſſion of our Faith, eſtabliſhed; and publikely confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſundry Acts of Parliament, and now of a long time hath been openly profeſſed by the Kings Majeſty, and whole body of this Realm, both in Burgh and Land. To the which Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and form of Religion, we willingly agree in our conſciences in all points, as unto Gods un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Truth and verity, grounded only upon His written Word. And therefore, we abhor and deteſt all contrary Religion, and Doctrine: But chiefly, all kind of Papiſtry, in general and particular heads, even as they are now damned, and confuted by the Word of God, and Kirk of <hi>Scotland:</hi> But in ſpeciall, we deteſt and refuſe the uſurped authority of that <hi>Romane</hi> Antichriſt upon the Scriptures of God, upon the Kirk, the Civil Magiſtrate, and conſciences of men; all his
<pb facs="tcp:53240:3"/>tyrannous lawes made upon indifferent things againſt our Chriſtian liberty: His erroneous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, againſt the ſufficiency of the written Word, the perfection of the Law, the Office of Chriſt, and His bleſſed Evangell: His corrupted Doctrine concerning original ſin, our natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability and rebellion to Gods Law, our Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation by Faith only, our imperfect Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and obedience to the Law, the nature, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and uſe of the Holy Sacraments, His five ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard Sacraments, With all his Rites, Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and falſe Doctrine, added to the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the true Sacraments without the Word of God: His cruell judgement againſt Infants, departing without the Sacrament: His abſolute neceſſity of Baptiſm, His blaſphemous opinion of Tranſubſtantiation, or reall preſence of Chriſts Body in the Elements, and receiving of the ſame by the wicked, or bodies of men, his diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with ſolemn Oaths, Perjuries; and degrees of Marriage forbidden in the Word: His cruelty againſt the innocent divorced: His deviliſh Maſſe: His blaſphemous Prieſt-hood: His profane Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the ſins of the dead and the quick: His Canonization of men, calling upon Angels or Saints departed, worſhipping of Imagery, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licts, and Croſſes, dedicating of Kirks; Altars, Dayes, Vowes to creatures; His Purgatory, Prayers for the dead; praying, or ſpeaking in a ſtrange language, with his Proceſſions, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb facs="tcp:53240:4"/>Leteny, and multitude of Advocates or Mediators: His manifold Orders, Auricular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: His deſperate and uncertain Repentance; His generall and doubtſome Faith; His ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men for their ſins: His Juſtifications by works, <hi>opus operatum,</hi> works of Supererogation, Merits, Pardons, Peregrinations, and Stations; His holy-water, baptiſing of Bells, conjuring of Spirits, croſſing, ſaning, anointing, conjuring, hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Gods good creatures, with the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious opinion joyned therewith: His worldly Monarchy, and wicked Hierarchie: His three ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn vowes, with all his ſhavellings of ſundry ſorts: His erroneous and bloudy decrees made at Trent, with all the ſubſcribers and approvers of that cruel and bloudy Band, conjured againſt the Kirk of God: And finally, We deteſt all his vain Allegories, Rites, Signes and Traditions, brought in the Kirk, without, or againſt the Word of God, and Doctrine of this true reformed Kirk: To the which we joyn our ſelves willingly, in Doctrine, Faith, Religion, Diſcipline, and uſe of the holy Sacraments, as lively members of the ſame, in Chriſt our Head: Promiſing and ſwearing by the Great Name of the Lord our God, that we ſhall continue in the Obedience of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Diſcipline of this Kirk, and ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ſame according to our vocation and power, all the dayes of our lives, under the pains contained in the Law, and danger both of
<pb facs="tcp:53240:4"/>Body and Soul, in the day of Gods fearful judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And ſeeing that many are ſtirred up by Satan, and that Romane Antichriſt, to promiſe, ſwear, ſubſcribe, and for a time uſe the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in the Kirk deceitfully, againſt their own conſciences, minding thereby, firſt, under the externall cloak of Religion, to corrupt and ſubvert ſecretly Gods true Religion within the Kirk, and afterward, when time may ſerve, to become open enemies and perſecutors of the ſame, under vain hopes of the Popes diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, deviſed againſt the Word of God, to his greater confuſion, and their double condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the day of the Lord Jeſus: We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, willing to take away all ſuſpition of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and of ſuch double dealing with God and his Kirk, Proteſt, and call <hi>The Searcher of all hearts</hi> for witneſſe that our mindes and hearts doe fully agree with this our <hi>Confeſſion, Promiſe, Oath,</hi> and <hi>Subſcription,</hi> ſo that We are not moved for any worldly reſpect, but are perſwaded only in our conſciences, through the knowledge and love of Gods true Religion, printed in our hearts, by the holy Spirit, as we ſhall anſwer to him in the day, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And becauſe we perceive, that the quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſtability of our Religion and Kirk, doth depend upon the ſafety and good behaviour of the Kings Majeſty, as upon a comfortable inſtrument of Gods mercy, granted to this Countrey, for
<pb facs="tcp:53240:5"/>the maintaining of this Kirk, and miniſtration of Juſtice amongſt us, we proteſt and promiſe with our hearts, under the ſame Oath, hand-writ, and pains, that we ſhall defend his perſon and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, with our goods, bodies, and lives, in the defence of Chriſt his Evangell, Liberties of our Countrey, miniſtration of Juſtice, and puniſhment of Iniquity, againſt all enemies within this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alm, or without, as we deſire our God to be a ſtrong and mercifull defender to us in the day of our death, and coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: To whom with the Father and the holy Spirit, be all honour and Glory eternally.</p>
               <p>LIke as many Acts of Parliament not only in generall do abrogate, annull, and reſcind all Laws, Statutes, Acts, Conſtitutions, Canons, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or municipal, with all other Ordinances and practique penalties whatſoever, made in prejudice of the true Religion and Profeſſors thereof: or, of the true Kirk diſcipline, juriſdiction and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thereof: Or in favours of Idolatry and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: Or of the Papiſticall Kirk: As <hi>Act.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 31. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 23. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>Act.</hi> 114. <hi>Parl.</hi> 12. of King <hi>James</hi> the ſixt, That Papiſtry and Superſtition may be utterly ſuppreſſed according to the intention of the Acts of Parliament re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in the 5 <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 20. King <hi>James</hi> 6. And to that end they ordain all Papiſts and Prieſts to be puniſhed by manifold Civil and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb facs="tcp:53240:5"/>pains, as adverſaries to Gods true Religion, preached, and by Law eſtabliſhed within this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, <hi>Act.</hi> 24. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. King <hi>James</hi> 6. as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enemies to all Chriſtian government, <hi>Act.</hi> 18. <hi>Parl.</hi> 16. King <hi>James</hi> 6. as rebellers and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanders of our Soveraign Lords Authority, <hi>Act.</hi> 47. <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. King <hi>James</hi> 6. and as Idolaters, <hi>Act.</hi> 104. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. King <hi>James</hi> 6. But alſo in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular (by and attour the Confeſſion of Faith) do aboliſh and condemn the Popes Authority and Juriſdiction out of this Land, and ordain the maintainers thereof to be puniſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 51. <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 106. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 114. <hi>Parl.</hi> 12. King <hi>James</hi> 6. do condemn the Popes erroneous doctrine, or any other erroneous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine repugnant to any of the Articles of the true and Chriſtian Religion publikely preached, and by Law eſtabliſhed in this Realm: And or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain the ſpreaders and makers of Books or Libels, or Letters, or Writes of that nature to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 46. <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 106. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 24. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. K. <hi>James</hi> 6. do condemn all Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme conform to the Popes Kirk and the Idolatry of the Maſſe, and ordain all ſayers, willfull hearers, and concealers of the Maſſe, the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers and reſetters of the Prieſts, Jeſuits, traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiquing Papiſts, to be puniſhed without any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception or reſtriction, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 120. <hi>Parl.</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 164. <hi>Parl.</hi> 13. <hi>Act.</hi> 193. <hi>Parl.</hi> 14. <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>Parl.</hi> 19. <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>Parl.</hi> 20. K. <hi>James</hi> 6. do condemn
<pb facs="tcp:53240:6"/>all erroneous books and writes containing erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous doctrine againſt the Religion preſently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, or containing ſuperſtitious Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies Papiſticall, whereby the people are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed, and ordain the home bringers of them to be puniſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 25. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. K. <hi>James</hi> 6. do condemn the monuments and dregs of bygane Idolatry, as going to the Croſſes, obſerving the Feaſtival dayes of Saints, and ſuch other ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and Papiſtical Rites, to the diſhonour of God, contempt of true Religion, and foſtering of great error among the people, and ordain the uſers of them to be puniſhed for the ſecond fault as Idolaters, <hi>Act.</hi> 104. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. K. <hi>James</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>LIKE AS many Acts of Parliament are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived For maintenance of Gods true and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, and the purity thereof in Doctrine and Sacraments of the true Church of God, the liberty and freedome thereof, in her National and Synodal Aſſemblies, Presbyteries, Seſſions, Policy, Diſcipline, and Juriſdiction thereof, as that puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Religion and liberty of the Church was uſed, profeſſed, exerciſed, preached and confeſſed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Reformation of Religion in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alm; As for inſtance <hi>the 99 Act. Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 23. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>Act.</hi> 114. <hi>Parl.</hi> 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 160. <hi>Parl.</hi> 13. <hi>of</hi> King <hi>James</hi> 6. ratified by the 4 <hi>Act.</hi> of King <hi>Charles.</hi> So that the 6 <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 1. and 68. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 6. of King <hi>James</hi> 6. in the year of God 1579. declare the Miniſters of the bleſſed Evangel, whom
<pb facs="tcp:53240:6"/>God of his mercy had raiſed up, or hereafter ſhould raiſe, agreeing with them that then lived in Doctrine, and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and the people that profeſſed Chriſt, as he was then offered in the Evangel, and doth communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the holy Sacraments, (as in the reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Kirks of this Realm they were publikely admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrate) according to the Confeſſion of Faith, to be the true and holy Kirk of Chriſt Jeſus within this Realm. And decern and declare all and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, who either gainſay the Word of the Evangel, received and approved as the heads of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, profeſſed in Parliament, in the year of God, 1560. ſpecified alſo in the firſt Parliament of King <hi>James</hi> 6. and ratified in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, more particularly do ſpecifie, or that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes the adminiſtration of the holy Sacraments, as they were then miniſtrated, to be no members of the ſaid Kirk within this Realm, and true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, preſently profeſſed, ſo long as they keep themſelves ſo divided from the ſociety of Chriſts Body: And the ſubſequent <hi>Act</hi> 69. <hi>Parl.</hi> 6. of King <hi>James</hi> 6. declares, that there is none other Face of Kirk, nor other Face of Religion, then was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently at that time, by the favour of God eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within this Realm, which therefore is ever ſtiled, <hi>Gods true Religion, Chriſts true Religion, the true and Chriſtian Religion, and a perfect Religion,</hi> Which, by manifold Acts of Parliament, all within this Realm, are bound to profeſſe to ſubſcribe the
<pb facs="tcp:53240:7"/>articles thereof, the Confeſſion of Faith, to recant all doctrine and errours, repugnant to any of the ſaid Articles, <hi>Act</hi> 4. and 9. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 45, 46, 47. <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 71. <hi>Parl.</hi> 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 106. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 24 <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>Act.</hi> 123. <hi>Parl.</hi> 12. <hi>Act.</hi> 194. and 197. <hi>Parl.</hi> 14. of King <hi>James</hi> 6. And all Magiſtrates, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifs, &amp;c. on the one part are ordained to ſearch, apprehend, and puniſh all contraveeners, For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Act</hi> 5. <hi>Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 104. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Act.</hi> 25. <hi>Parl.</hi> 11. K. <hi>James</hi> 6. And that notwithſtanding of the Kings Majeſties licences on the contrary which are diſcharged and declared to be of no force in ſo far as they tend in any wayes to the prejudice and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the execution of the Acts of Parliament againſt Papiſts and adverſaries of true Religion, <hi>Act.</hi> 106. <hi>Parl.</hi> 7. K. <hi>James</hi> 6. On the other part in the 47. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 3. K. <hi>James</hi> 6. It is declared and ordained, ſeeing the cauſe of Gods true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and his Highneſſe authority are ſo joyned, as the hurt of the one is common to both, and that none ſhall be reputed as loyall and faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to our Soveraign Lord, or his authority, but be puniſhable as rebellers and gainſtanders of the ſame, who ſhall not give their Confeſſion, and make their Profeſſion of the ſaid true Religion, and that they who after defection ſhall give the Confeſſion of their Faith of new, they ſhall promiſe to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue therein in time coming, to maintain our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lords Authority, and at the uttermoſt of their power to fortifie, aſſiſt and maintain the true
<pb facs="tcp:53240:7"/>Preachers and Profeſſors of Chriſts Evangel againſt whatſoever enemies and gainſtanders of the ſame: and namely, againſt all ſuch (of whatſoever nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eſtate or degree they be of) that have joyned and bound themſelves; or have aſſiſted, or aſſiſt to ſet forward and execute the cruel decrees of the Counſel of <hi>Trent,</hi> contrary to the true Preachers and Profeſſors of the Word of God, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated word by word in the Articles of Pacificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at <hi>Perth</hi> the 23 of <hi>February,</hi> 1572. approved by Parliament the laſt of <hi>April</hi> 1573. Ratified in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament 1587. and related, <hi>Act.</hi> 123. <hi>parl.</hi> 12. of King <hi>James</hi> 6. with this addition, that they are bound to reſiſt all treaſonable uproars and hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, raiſed againſt the true Religion, the Kings Majeſty, and the true Profeſſors. LIKE AS all Liedges are bound to maintain the Kings Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Royall Perſon, and Authority, the Authority of Parliament, without the which neither any Laws or lawfull Judicatories can be eſtabliſhed, <hi>Act.</hi> 130. <hi>Act.</hi> 131. <hi>parl.</hi> 8. King <hi>James</hi> 6. and the Subjects liberties, who ought only to live and be governed by the Kings laws, the common laws of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alm allanerly, <hi>Act.</hi> 48. <hi>parl.</hi> 3. King <hi>James</hi> the 1. <hi>Act.</hi> 79. <hi>parl.</hi> 6. King <hi>James</hi> the 4. repeated in the <hi>Act.</hi> 131. <hi>parl.</hi> 8. King <hi>James</hi> 6. Which if they be innovated or prejudged the Commiſſion anent the Union of the two Kingdomes of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> which is the ſole <hi>Act of the</hi> 17. <hi>Parl. of King James</hi> 6. declares ſuch confuſion would
<pb facs="tcp:53240:8"/>enſue, as this Realm could be no more a free Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, becauſe by the fundamentall laws, ancient priviledges, offices, and liberties of this Kingdom, not only the Princely Authority of his Majeſties Royall diſcent hath been theſe many ages main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, but alſo the peoples ſecurity of their Land, livings, rights, offices, liberties, and dignities pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. And therefore for the preſervation of the ſaid true Religion, Lawes, and Liberties of this Kingdome, it is ſtatute by the 8 <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated in the</hi> 99. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Ratified in the</hi> 23. <hi>Act. Parl.</hi> 11. <hi>and</hi> 114. <hi>Act. parl.</hi> 12. <hi>of K. James</hi> 6. <hi>and</hi> 4. <hi>Act of K. Charles,</hi> that all Kings and princes at their Coronation and reception of their Princely authority, ſhall make their faithfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe by their ſolemn Oath in the preſence of the Eternal God, that enduring the whole time of their lives, they ſhall ſerve the ſame Eternal God to the uttermoſt of their power, according as he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in his moſt holy Word, contained in the Old and New Teſtament: And according to the ſame Word, ſhall maintain the true Religion of Chriſt Jeſus, the preaching of his holy Word, the due and right miniſtration of the Sacraments now received and preached within this Realm (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Confeſſion of Faith immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding) and ſhall aboliſh and gainſtand all falſe Religion contrary to the ſame, and ſhall rule the people, committed to their charge, according to the will and command of God, revealed in his
<pb facs="tcp:53240:8"/>foreſaid Word, and according to the laudable Lawes and Conſtitutions received in this Realm, no wayes repugnant to the ſaid will of the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall GOD, and ſhall procure to the uttermoſt of their power, to the Kirk of God, and whole Chriſtian People, true and perfect peace in all time coming, and that they ſhall be carefull to root out of their Empire all Hereticks and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the true worſhip of God, who ſhall be convicted by the true Kirk of God, of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid crimes, which was alſo obſerved by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty at his Coronation at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 1633. as may be ſeen in the order of the Coronation.</p>
               <p>IN OBEDIENCE to the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, conform to the practiſe of the godly in former times, and according to the laud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able example of our Worthy and Religious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors, and of many yet living amongſt us, which was warranted alſo by Act of Councel, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding a general Band to be made and ſubſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Majeſties Subjects of all ranks, for two cauſes: One was, for defending the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as it was then Reformed, and is expreſſed in the Confeſſion of Faith, above written, and a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer large Confeſſion eſtabliſhed by ſundry Acts of lawfull General Aſſemblies, and of Parliament, unto which it hath relation ſet down in publick Catechiſms, and which had been for many years with a bleſſing from Heaven preached and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this Kirk and Kingdom, as Gods undoubted
<pb facs="tcp:53240:9"/>Truth, grounded only upon his written Word. The other cauſe was, for maintaining the Kings Majeſty his Perſon and Eſtate: the true Worſhip of God, and the Kings Authority being ſo ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyned, as that they had the ſame friends, and common enemies, and did ſtand and fall together. And finally, being convinced in our minds, and confeſſing with our mouths that the preſent and ſucceeding generations in this Land, are bound to keep the foreſaid National Oath and Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on inviolable. We Noblemen, Barons, Gentlemen, Burgeſſes, Miniſters, and Commons underſcribing, conſidering divers times before, and eſpecially at this time, the danger of the true reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of the Kings honour, and of the publick peace of the Kingdom, by the manifold innovations and evils, generally contained, and particularly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in our late ſupplications, complaints, and proteſtations, Do hereby profeſſe, and before God, his Angels, and the world, ſolemnly declare, that with our whole hearts we agree and reſolve all the dayes of our life conſtantly to adhere unto, and to defend the foreſaid true Religion, and (forbearing the practiſe of all novations, already introduced in the matter of the worſhip of God, or approbation of the corruptions of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Governments of the Kirk or civil places and power of Kirk-men, till they be tryed and allowed in free Aſſemblies, and in Parliaments) to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by all means lawfull to recover the purity
<pb facs="tcp:53240:9"/>and liberty of the Goſpel, as it was eſtabliſhed and profeſſed before the foreſaid novations. And becauſe after due examination we plainly perceive, and undoubtedly believe, that the innovations and evils contained in our Supplications, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and Proteſtations have no warrant of the Word of God, are contrary to the articles of the foreſaid Confeſſions, to the intention and meaning of the bleſſed reformers of Religion in this Land, to the above written Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and do ſenſibly tend to the re-eſtabliſhing of the Popiſh Religion and tyranny, and to the ſubverſion and ruine of the true reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of our liberties, lawes, and eſtates; We alſo declare, that the foreſaid Confeſſions are to be interpreted, and ought to be underſtood of the forſaid novations and evils no leſſe than if eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them had been expreſſed in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Confeſſions, and that we are oblieged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and abhorre them amongſt other particular heads of Papiſtry abjured therein. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from the knowledge and conſciences of our duty to God, to our King and Countrey, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any worldly reſpect or inducement, ſo far as humane infirmity will ſuffer, wiſhing a further meaſure of the grace of God for this effect; We promiſe, and ſwear by the great Name of the Lord our GOD, to continue in the Profeſſion and obedience of the foreſaid Religion, That we ſhall defend the ſame and reſiſt all theſe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:53240:10"/>errours and corruptions, according to our vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and to the uttermoſt of that power that God hath put in our hands, all the dayes of our life. And in like manner, with the ſame heart we declare before God and Men, that we have no intention nor deſire to attempt any thing that may turn to the diſhonour of God, or to the diminution of the Kings greatneſſe and authority: but on the contrary, we promiſe and ſwear, that we ſhall to the uttermoſt of our power, with our means and lives, ſtand to the defence of our dread Soveraign the Kings Majeſty, his Perſon, and Authority, in the defence and preſervation of the foreſaid true Religion, Liberties and Lawes of the Kingdom: As alſo, to the mutual defence and aſſiſtance every one of us of another, in the ſame cauſe of maintaining the true Religion, and his Majeſties Authority, with our beſt counſel, our bodies, means, and whole power againſt all ſorts of perſons whatſoever; So that whatſoever ſhal be done to the leaſt of us for that cauſe, ſhall be taken as done to us all in general, and to every one of us in particular: And that we ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther directly nor indirectly ſuffer our ſelves to be divided or withdrawn by whatſoever ſuggeſtion, or allurement, or terrour from this bleſſed and loyall Conjunction, nor ſhall caſt in any let or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment, that may ſtay or hinder any ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution as by common conſent ſhall be found to conduce for ſo good ends. But on the contrary,
<pb facs="tcp:53240:10"/>ſhall by all lawfull means labour to further and promove the ſame. And if any ſuch dangerous and diviſive motion ſhould be made to us by word or writ; we, and every one of us, ſhall either ſuppreſſe it, or if need be, ſhall incontinent make the ſame known; that it may be timouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated: Neither do we fear the foul aſperſions of rebellion, combinations, or what elſe our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries from their craft and malice would put upon us, ſeeing what we do is ſo well warranted, and ariſeth from an unfained deſire to maintain the true worſhip of God, the Majeſty of our King, and peace of the Kingdom, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon happineſſe of our ſelves and poſterity. And becauſe we cannot look for a bleſſing from God upon our proceedings, except with our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſubſcription we joyn ſuch a life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, as beſeemeth Chriſtians, who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed their Covenant with God; We therefore faithfully promiſe, for our ſelves, our followers, and all others under us, both in publick, in our particular Familes, and perſonal carriage, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep our ſelves within the bounds of Chriſtian liberty, and to be good examples of all godlineſſe, ſoberneſſe, and righteouſneſſe, and of every duty we owe to God and Man. And that this our Union and Conjunction may be obſerved without violation, We call the living GOD, the Searcher of our hearts, to witneſſe, who knoweth this to be our ſincere Deſire and unfained Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,
<pb facs="tcp:53240:11"/>as we ſhal anſwer to JESUS CHRIST in the great Day, and under the pain of Gods everlaſting wrath, and of infamy, and loſſe of all honour and reſpect in this World, moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeeching the Lord to ſtrengthen us by His holy Spirit for this end; and to bleſſe our deſires and proceedings with a happy ſucceſſe, that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Righteouſneſſe may flouriſh in the Land, to the glory of God, the honour of our King, and peace and comfort of us all, In wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whereof, we have ſubſcribed with our hands all the premiſſes.</p>
               <p>The article of this Covenant, which was at the firſt ſubſcription referred to the determination of the General Aſſembly being determined. And thereby the Five Articles of <hi>Perth,</hi> The govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kirk by Biſhops, The civil places and power of Kirkmen upon the reaſons and grounds contained in the Acts of the General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly declared to be unlawfull within this Kirk, We ſubſcribe according to the determination foreſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:53240:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
